<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Geekery | Fabrizio (Fritz) Stelluto]]></title>
  <link href="http://gotofritz.net/blog/cat/geekery/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://gotofritz.net/"/>
  <updated>2015-04-04T03:03:33+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://gotofritz.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Useful Alfred workflows for web development]]></title>
    <link href="http://gotofritz.net/blog/geekery/alfred-workflows-web-development/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-04T01:51:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://gotofritz.net/blog/geekery/useful-alfred-color-tool-for-os-x</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.alfredapp.com/">Alfred App</a> has a couple of useful workflow for web developers.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Alfred App is one of the things that make working on OS X a pleasure. There are lots of useful workflows out there, and using a folder inside Dropbox as the sync folder (Preferences &gt; Advanced &gt; Syncing.. ) allows me to share them among my work and home machines.</p>

<p>Here are a couple of workflows I find useful for web development.</p>

<h2><a href="http://www.packal.org/workflow/colors">Colors</a></h2>

<p>I can type a color directly into Alfred, say <code>#ff0000</code> or <code>rgb 1,45,87</code> and Alfred will show me a list of conversions in other formats, with a swatch in the color itself. Use <code>c name</code> for a CSS color name, say <code>c red</code>.</p>

<h2><a href="https://github.com/willfarrell/alfred-encode-decode-workflow">Encode/Decode</a></h2>

<p>Quickly convert from HTML or URL encoded text to plain by typing <code>decode &lt;TEXT&gt;</code>, or viceversa with  <code>encode &lt;TEXT&gt;</code>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Directory listings in Apache 2.4]]></title>
    <link href="http://gotofritz.net/blog/geekery/directory-listings-in-apache-2-4/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-07T23:14:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://gotofritz.net/blog/geekery/directory-listings-in-apache-2-dot-4</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yosemite updates Apache to 2.4. A couple of things stopped working from my previous installation, including autogenerated directory listings. Here's how I got them back.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Yosemite updates Apache from 2.2 to 2.4</h2>

<p>It copies the old httpd.conf to <code>/etc/apache2/httpd.conf~previous</code> and replaces it with a vannilla one. Annoying, but not too painful to replace, and it doesn't touch the vhosts. <a href="https://httpd.apache.org/docs/trunk/new_features_2_4.html">The list of 2.4 changes</a> doesn't include anything I actually use. Sadly that doesn't mean nothing important has changed - rather, they didn't bother to list things that matter to me.</p>

<h2>Apache "directory listing forbidden"</h2>

<p>I used to rely on the automatic directory listings generated by mod_autoidex, but they has stopped working. The logs give the message <code>No matching DirectoryIndex (index.html) found, and server-generated directory index forbidden by Options directive</code>. "Impossible!" I cry, the settings are right, and they always worked.</p>

<p>This is the DocumentRoot fragment of httpd.conf. <code>+Indexes</code> is the bit which is supposed to turn on auto-indexing. I use /Library/... for not so important documents I need to put under a webserver for whatever reason.
``` bash
DocumentRoot "/Library/WebServer/Documents"
<Directory "/Library/WebServer/Documents"></p>

<pre><code>Options +Indexes +FollowSymLinks
# etc
</code></pre>

<p></Directory>
```</p>

<p>And this is one of the virtual hosts. For serious dev work, I put my vhosts somewhere other than /Library/...
``` bash
<VirtualHost *:80></p>

<pre><code>DocumentRoot "/pth/to/somewhere/completely/different"
ServerName my-virtual-host.dev
ErrorLog "/private/var/log/apache2/my-virtual-host.dev-error_log"
CustomLog "/private/var/log/apache2/my-virtual-host.dev-access_log" common
</code></pre>

<p></VirtualHost>
```</p>

<p>What has changed is that now the options for DocumentRoot don't automatically carry over to folders which are not subdirectories of DocumentRoot. This can be easily fixed by changing virtual hosts to
``` bash
<VirtualHost *:80></p>

<pre><code>DocumentRoot "/pth/to/somewhere/completely/different"
ServerName my-virtual-host.dev
ErrorLog "/private/var/log/apache2/my-virtual-host.dev-error_log"
CustomLog "/private/var/log/apache2/my-virtual-host.dev-access_log" common
&lt;Directory "/pth/to/somewhere/completely/different"&gt;
    Options +Indexes
&lt;/Directory&gt;
</code></pre>

<p></VirtualHost>
```</p>

<p>That proves what the problem is, but it sucks having to do that for every virtual host. The solution is to add the directive for the common parent folder of all my virtual hosts in httpd.conf</p>

<p>``` bash
<Directory "/parent/of/somewhere/completely/different"></p>

<pre><code>Options +Indexes
</code></pre>

<p></Directory>
```</p>

<h2>Restart apache and all is well</h2>

<p>After a <code>sudo apachectl restart</code> everything works fine.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Injecting local IP Address into a file with bash]]></title>
    <link href="http://gotofritz.net/blog/geekery/injecting-local-ip-address-into-a-file-with-bash/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-03T14:24:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://gotofritz.net/blog/geekery/injecting-local-ip-address-into-a-file-with-bash</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sometimes there are some config file on which you have no control for which you need to change an IP address to that of your current dev machine. Here's how I fix that with a bash script.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>A good place to put bash scripts</h2>

<p>I have a <code>bin</code> folder inside my user folder. It is in the <code>$PATH</code>, meaning every script file in there can be executed as a script from anywhere. In there I create a text file called <code>fix-config-PROJECT</code>. Yes, I make one per project, because I hard code the paths of the files to change. This could evolve into something more complex if the need arises, but the setup I have so far has served me well so far.</p>

<p><code>bash
nano ~/bin/fix-config-PROJECT
</code></p>

<h2>The script file</h2>

<p>``` bash</p>

<h1>!/bin/bash</h1>

<p>IP=<code>ifconfig  | grep inet | grep -v inet6 | tail -n1 | awk '{print $2}'</code>
for file in "launchpad/src/main/tomcat/conf/context.xml" "path/to/etc.xml"
do
  svn revert $file
  sed -i "" "s/localhost/$IP/g" $file
done
```</p>

<h2>Script breakdown</h2>

<dl class="code-breakdown">
  <dt class="long-line">IP=`ifconfig  | grep inet | grep -v inet6 | tail -n1 | awk '{print $2}'`</dt>
  <dd class="long-line">This runs a series of commands one after the other, using <code>|</code> to pass the result of each command to the next. The ` at the beginning and end put the result into a variable <code>$IP</code></dd>

  <dt>ifconfig</dt>
  <dd>From the manpage: "The ifconfig utility is used to assign an address to a network interface and/or configure network interface parameters". Used without parameters, it returns a big chunk of text with current settings. The IP address is in there somewhere.</dd>

  <dt>grep inet</dt>
  <dt>grep -v inet6</dt>
  <dd>extracts the lines from that chunk of text which have "inet" in it, but not "inet6"</dd>

  <dt>tail -n1</dt>
  <dd>take the last of these lines</dd>

  <dt>awk '{print $2}'</dt>
  <dd>At this point we have a string like <code>inet 192.168.2.108 netmask 0xffffff00 broadcast 192.168.2.255</code>. Awk can be used to extract the 192... from it. Awk is a utilities that processes a line of text by splitting into fields where blank spaces are - it is used for handling database dumps etc. In this case, it is basically saying that after it's split the line into fields (which it does automatically), it should print out the second field and throw away the rest.</dd>

  <dt class="long-line">for file in "launchpad/src/main/tomcat/conf/context.xml" "path/to/etc.xml"</dt>
  <dd class="long-line">The files I need to process are listed out one after the other. This is good enough for my use case. Note that the paths are not absolute, so that I can use the same command in different svn branches. What this line does is looping through each file</dd>

  <dt class="long-line">svn revert $file</dt>
  <dt class="long-line">sed -i "" "s/localhost/$IP/g" $file</dt>
  <dd class="long-line">First I revert the latest changes, then I make new ones. This time using sed, a utility which processes text a line at the time, transforming it on the way. The <code>-i ""</code> means to process the file in place (as opposed to create a copy), without creating a backup. The substitution is simple, I simply change all occurrences of <code>locahost</code> with the IP address from earlier</dd>
</dl>


<h2>Running the script</h2>

<p>I can now run the script from anywhere on my machine, usually as
<code>bash
cd PROJECT/branch_x
fix-config-PROJECT
</code>
and then all the config files are changed as required, and I can access my local version site from tablets etc using the IP address.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ensure an explicit number of expectations within a spec in Jasmine]]></title>
    <link href="http://gotofritz.net/blog/geekery/ensure-explicit-number-expectations-within-spec-jasmine/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-22T23:36:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://gotofritz.net/blog/geekery/ensure-an-explicit-number-of-expectations-within-a-spec-in-jasmine</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>QUnit and js-test-driver have ways of specifying how many assertions will be executed in a test case (<a href="http://api.qunitjs.com/expect/" title="[new window] expect() | QUnit API Documentation" target="_blank">expect</a> and <a href="https://code.google.com/p/js-test-driver/wiki/TestCase#expectAsserts(count)" title="[new window] TestCase - js-test-driver - Everything you need to know about writing tests. - Remote javascript console - Google Project Hosting" target="_blank">expectAsserts</a> respectively) but Jasmine doesn't. But it can still be done - here's how.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Why would anyone want to count the number of expectations in a test</h2>

<p>Normally Jasmine specs are pretty straightforward (assuming <code>systemUnderTest</code> is defined somewhere else):</p>

<p><code>js
it("does something really simple", function () {
  var actual = systemUnderTest.methodToTest(arg);
  expect(actual).not.toBe(true);
});
</code>
There are no branches, and you know Jasmine is going to run through all the expectations, one after the other. But it gets more complicated when loops, or async specs are involved. For example</p>

<p>``` js
it("throws exceptions for all wrong arguments", function () {
  var methodWrapper = function (arg) { systemUnderTest.methodToTest(arg); }</p>

<pre><code>, wrongArgs = [new Date(),
               Math.random(),
               false,
               null,
               {a: 1, b: 2},
               "a string",
               [1, 2],
               undefined,
               function () { return 123; }
               ]
;
</code></pre>

<p>  wrongArgs
  .forEach(function (arg) {</p>

<pre><code>expect(methodWrapper.bind(null, arg)).toThrow();
</code></pre>

<p>  });</p>

<p>});
```</p>

<p>Here there is an array of arguments, each of which should cause the method <code>systemUnderTest.methodToTest</code> to throw an exception. So we loop through the array of arguments, and run an expectation for each of them.
We have to wrap the call to <code>methodToTest</code> in a function, because it's going to throw an exception - the function <code>methodWrapper</code> is a partial used by <code>.bind</code> to generate such a function. So each iteration of the loop will have a new version of <code>methodWrapper</code>, with <code>arg</code> already plugged in. Then <code>expect</code> can run it, catch the exception, and pass the test.</p>

<p>This is still simple enough, there is only one loop with one statement in it. But you can see how this could easily get out of hand. What if the code was a little more complex, and for some reason the expectations in the loop are not executed? It will look like the test has passed, and you will never know the difference.</p>

<p>The js-test-driver page gives another example, using workers (adapted to Jasmine)
``` js
it("shows what could go wrong", function () {
  var worker = new Worker(),</p>

<pre><code>, doSomething = {}
;
</code></pre>

<p>  worker.listener = function (work){</p>

<pre><code>expect(work).toBe(doSomething);
</code></pre>

<p>  };
  worker.perform(doSomething);
};
```</p>

<p>If the worker doesn't call the callback function, then the expectation will not be run, and once again, it will look like the test has passed when it hasn't.</p>

<h2>Defining the number of expected assertions in Jasmine</h2>

<p>Jasmine doesn't have a simple way to tell how many assertions have run, but digging into the code I found where to get the information - in version 1.3 at least: <code>this.env.currentSpec.results_.passedCount</code></p>

<p>Therefore the examples above can be rewritten as</p>

<p>``` js mark:20
it("throws exceptions for all wrong arguments", function () {
  var methodWrapper = function (arg) { systemUnderTest.methodToTest(arg); }</p>

<pre><code>, wrongArgs = [new Date(),
               Math.random(),
               false,
               null,
               {a: 1, b: 2},
               "a string",
               [1, 2],
               undefined,
               function () { return 123; }
               ]
;
</code></pre>

<p>  wrongArgs
  .forEach(function (arg) {</p>

<pre><code>expect(methodWrapper.bind(null, arg)).toThrow();
</code></pre>

<p>  });</p>

<p>  expect(this.env.currentSpec.results_.passedCount).toEqual(wrongArgs.length)
});
```
and</p>

<p>``` js mark:10
it("shows what could go wrong", function () {
  var worker = new Worker(),</p>

<pre><code>, doSomething = {}
;
</code></pre>

<p>  worker.listener = function (work){</p>

<pre><code>expect(work).toBe(doSomething);
</code></pre>

<p>  };
  worker.perform(doSomething);
  expect(this.env.currentSpec.results_.passedCount).toBe(1);
};
```</p>

<h2>A note on compatibility</h2>

<p>This will work, but only in version 1.3 - with the new 2.0 version <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!topic/jasmine-js/IyZt7cPmBWo" title="[new window] Removing .currentSpec from env breaks tests in jasmine 2.0 (since rc5) - Google Groups" target="_blank"><code>currentSpec</code> remains private</a>.
There was a plugin, <a href="https://github.com/dfkaye/jasmine-intercept" title="[new window] dfkaye/jasmine-intercept" target="_blank">jasmine-intercept</a>,  that used to take care of that, but apparently it has now been superseded by <a href="https://github.com/dfkaye/where.js" title="[new window] dfkaye/where.js" target="_blank">where.js</a>. I haven't had a chance to look into that yet, for now I'll stick to my quick and dirty workaround.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Inserting CDATA into a Sublime Text snippet]]></title>
    <link href="http://gotofritz.net/blog/geekery/inserting-cdata-into-sublime-text-snippet/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-05T18:20:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://gotofritz.net/blog/geekery/inserting-cdata-into-a-sublime-text-snippet</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://sublime-text-unofficial-documentation.readthedocs.org/en/latest/reference/snippets.html" title="[new window] Snippets — Sublime Text Unofficial Documentation" target="_blank">Sublime Text Snippets</a> are XML documents, with the body of the snippet is inside a CDATA node. So what happens if you need the body of the snippet to have a CDATA of its own?</p>

<!--more-->


<p>XML documents cannot have nested CDATA blocks, so any CDATA you put in there is illegal. The problem is not the opening tag itself, the <code>&lt;![CDATA[</code>, which is just treated as part of the data, i.e. ignored. The problem is the closing tag, the <code>]]&gt;</code> - it will close the CDATA before you need to, so any XML after that will likely be invalid.</p>

<h2>Sublime insertion points</h2>

<p>Snippets can have insertion points: <code>${1}</code> is where the cursor will be when you create the snippet, <code>${2}</code> is where it will go to when you tab, and so on. Incidentally, <code>${1:DEFAULT}</code> will select the word "DEFAULT" and leave the cursor there, so you can just tab away or type something to overwrite it. Anyway.</p>

<p>It turns out you can use the insertion point <code>${-1}</code> too. It does absolutely nothing at all, which is just what we need - something that can be used to break up the <code>]]&gt;</code> without doing anything at all.</p>

<p>Let's say we want to create a snippet with this body, and we want "TITLE" to be selectable, with one insertion point in each CDATA</p>

<p><code>xml
&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?&gt;
  &lt;title&gt;&lt;![CDATA[TITLE]]&gt;&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;description&gt;&lt;![CDATA[]]&gt;&lt;/description&gt;
  &lt;source&gt;&lt;![CDATA[]]&gt;&lt;/source&gt;
</code></p>

<p>Here's how to use the <code>${-1}</code> trick to break up the CDATA blocks - note how it goes in between the <code>]]</code> and the closing <code>&gt;</code></p>

<p>``` xml
<snippet></p>

<pre><code>&lt;content&gt;&lt;![CDATA[&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>  <title>&lt;![CDATA[${1:TITLE}]]${-1}></title>
  <description>&lt;![CDATA[$2]]${-1}></description>
  <source>&lt;![CDATA[$3]]${-1}></source>
]]&gt;</content></p>

<pre><code>&lt;!-- Optional: Set a tabTrigger to define how to trigger the snippet --&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;tabTrigger&gt;hello&lt;/tabTrigger&gt; --&gt;
&lt;!-- Optional: Set a scope to limit where the snippet will trigger --&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;scope&gt;source.python&lt;/scope&gt; --&gt;
</code></pre>

<p></snippet>
```</p>

<p>That's rather simple once you know how.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
