<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Living | Fabrizio (Fritz) Stelluto]]></title>
  <link href="http://gotofritz.net/blog/cat/living/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://gotofritz.net/"/>
  <updated>2015-04-04T03:03:33+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://gotofritz.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[German language resources]]></title>
    <link href="http://gotofritz.net/blog/living/german-learning-resources"/>
    <updated>2012-07-21T15:12:18+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://gotofritz.net/blog/living/german-learning-resources</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>These are the resources  I use in my efforts to learn German. Ich hoffe, dass sie nützlich sind.</p>

<!--more-->




<dl class="normal">
<dt><a href="http://www.pons.eu/">Pons</a></dt>
<dd>Pons has quickly become my online <strong>English-German dictionary</strong> of choice - it beats the others hands down. It has <strong>pronunciation samples</strong>, <strong>sample sentences</strong>, phonetic alphabet, ...</dt>

<dt><a href="http://bildwoerterbuch.pons.eu/static/all/bildwoerterbuch_startseite">Pons picture lexicon (Bildwörterbuch)</a></dt>
<dd>...and a <strong>picture dictionary</strong>. Helps a lot with building up a vocabulary, an important part of a language learning.</dt>

<dt><a href="http://translate.google.com/#en|de|">[en] -> [de]</a><br>
<a href="http://translate.google.com/#de|en|">[de] -> [en]</a></dt>
<dd>Google <strong>translation</strong>, often quite wrong but still very useful</dt>

<dt><a href="http://www.forvo.com/">Forvo</a></dt>
<dd><strong>Pronunciation samples</strong> - very comprehensive</dt>

<dt><a href="http://www.linguee.de/deutsch-englisch/search">Linguee</a></dt>
<dd>Contains <strong>translated sample sentences</strong> (they seem to be from EU documents).</dt>

<dt><a href="http://www.canoo.net/">Canoonet</a></dt>
<dd><strong>Declination tables</strong> and some <strong>grammar</strong></dt>

<dt><a href="http://de.thefreedictionary.com/">Deutsches Wörterbuch / German Dictionary</a></dt>
<dd>A <strong>German dictionary</strong> with <strong>untranslated sample sentences</strong></dt>

<dt><a href="http://www.duden.de/">Duden dictionary</a></dt>
<dd>Another good <strong>dictionary</strong>, although I don't use it as much</dt>

<dt><a href="http://www.dwds.de/">DWDS</a></dt>
<dd>Has a lot of info in there, in a fiddly interface: <strong>German dictionary</strong>, <strong>untranslated sample sentences</strong> scraped from newspapers, <strong>German thesaurus</strong>, <strong>etymological dictionary</strong>,  <strong>pronunciation samples</strong>, even <strong>statistics</strong> on how word usage changed throughout the century</dt>

<dt><a href="http://dict.leo.org/ende?lang=de&amp;lp=ende">dict.leo.org</a></dt>
<dd>Very popular <strong>English-German dictionary</strong> and <strong>forum</strong>, it does have some funny entries. Android app is useful.</dt>

<dt><a href="http://www.uiowa.edu/~acadtech/phonetics/german/frameset.html">Phonetics: The sounds of German</a></dt>
<dd>Old school Flash app with animated diagrams and <strong>pronunciation samples</strong>.</dt>

<dt><a href="http://www.youtube.com/user/easyonlinegerman">Easy online German - YouTube</a></dt>
<dd>A series of <strong>pronunciation sample</strong> videos put on youtube by a woman called Sonja. She's very thorough, and has easy to follow <strong>pronunciation tips</strong></dt>

<dt><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wASqDHXjYFQ&amp;feature=related">The Global Experience German guide</a></dt>
<dd>A series of <strong>pronunciation sample</strong> videos explained in German with subtitles. Not as good as Sonja's.</dt>

<dt><a href="http://duolingo.com/">Duolingo</a></dt>
<dd>A complete <strong>German course</strong> like the commercial Rosetta Stone, but free.</dt>

<dt><a href="http://german.about.com/">About.com Learn German</a></dt>
<dd>German <strong>grammar</strong> and <strong>lessons</strong></dt>

<dt><a href="http://www.dw.de/dw/0,,2469,00.html">Deutsche Welle Learn Center</a></dt>
<dd>A complete German course with video <strong>lessons</strong> and tests</dt>

<dt><a href="http://forum.wordreference.com/search.php?search_type=1">Wordreference forum</a></dt>
<dd>A <strong>forum</strong>, can be useful some times, although like in all forums there is some weird stuff in there</dt>

</dl>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Most plastic containers are not recyclable]]></title>
    <link href="http://gotofritz.net/blog/living/most-plastic-containers-not-reusable"/>
    <updated>2011-06-13T18:45:08+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://gotofritz.net/blog/living/most-plastic-containers-not-reusable</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/universal-recycling-sign-symbols.png" alt="The SPI Resin Identification Symbol System" /></p>

<p>Plastic labelling can be misleading, because you need to know what the numbers mean to know whether an item is safe to re-use as your lunchbox. Most aren't.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>What do the plastic recycling symbol mean?</h2>

<p>The bottom line: plastic containers from groups 2, 4, and 5 below can be re-used, but avoid the others.</p>

<dl class="code-breakdown">
<dt>1: PET or PETE</dt>
<dd>This is commonly used in drink bottles. It is recyclable (mostly for textiles and carpets) but it is meant to be used once and <b>should not be reused at home</b>, not because of the toxins, but because it breaks down and it becomes a breeding ground for bacteria.<br>
    PET or PETE: Polyethylene Terephthalate</dd>

<dt>2: HDPE</dt>
<dd>Used in milk bottles, yogurt tubs, cereal box liners. This is recyclable (pipes and plastic furniture) and has low risk of toxin leeching.<br>
<b>Reusable and recyclable</b><br>
    HDPE: High Density Polyethylene</dd>

<dt>3: V or PVC</dt>
<dd>This is widely used but not in the food industry. Everything that is bad about plastic - it can even releases poison in the air. It used in some cling films and children toys. <br><b>Toxic and non-recyclable</b><br>
    V or PVC: polyvinyl Chloride</dd>

<dt>#4: LDPE</dt>
<dd>Strong and flexible, used in cabling, medical industry and as shopping bags, but also for food packaging such as squeezable bottles like honey or baby bottles. <br><b>Recyclable and reusable</b><br>
    LDPE: Low density Polyethylene</dd>

<dt>#5: PP</dt>
<dd>Another good one, tupperware and baby bottles are made from this. <br><b>Reusable and recyclable</b><br>
    PP: Polypropylene</dd>

<dt>#6: PS</dt>
<dd>Widely used (egg cartons, disposable cups) but it is know to leach toxins into foods. Styrofoam belongs to this group. Another bad one. <br><b>Not easily recyclable; better not to reuse</b><br>
    PS: Polystyrene</dd>

<dt>#7: Other</dt>
<dd>Anything else - this group includes both harmless and compostable plastics made from vegetables, and others such as policarbonate who can leach potential hormone disruptors. <br><b>Not recyclable and not reusable</b> (unless the precise type is known to be harmless).<br>
    Other: anything not covered above</dd>
</dl>


<h2>Who invented the plastic codes?</h2>

<p>The symbols (officially called the SPI Resin Identification Symbol System) were devised in 1988 by a trade body, the SPI (Society of Plastic Industry). Some people feel they should be changed to something that gives a visual clue as to whether the plastic is recyclable or not. If you'd like to add your voice, here is the <a href="http://www.plasticsindustry.org/applications/forms-bd/formDisplay.cfm?FormID=6969">feedback form on the SPI website</a> - you never know.</p>

<h2>More info</h2>

<p>This info is readily available on <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Resin_identification_code">WikiPedia</a> and via <a href="http://google.com/search?q=plastic+labelling">Google search</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
